[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right everyone let's begin
welcome to the stoa a place where we
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice
edge of this very moment and today
we have the return of bonita roy
[Music]
so i hope everyone heard the hype if not
i'll play it again multiple times
um yes so bonita is back
uh benita was uh here from the beginning
she was doing something called the
psycho technology playground at the stoa
and i think it went for like almost 15
sessions and then it ended
and my heart was broken and then since
then i was begging bonita to come back
and then she finally relented and she
said okay i'll be a sense-making
residence for october
and the series will be called the hollow
um
so i'm really excited uh about that and
uh
so it's the sunspeaker in residence
series it happens uh over a month
uh for four sessions the same time the
same day um
and each each series has an mc and this
series mc is rain river
rain is um everyone loves rain uh
she's freakishly intelligent and awesome
and so we're lucky to have her here
uh and so i'm gonna take in rain right
now rain if you want to say anything
more about yourself
introduce bonita and then she'll talk
about the q a protocols
um and then yeah and then we'll we'll
get started we're here for 90 minutes in
total
uh so that being said i will take reign
in
thanks peter hi everyone um
i am really honored to be emceeing this
session
i joined punita's last series um
maybe at the second session and was
immediately hooked
um i find bonita's teachings to be
incredibly insightful she's super well
informed about
various sense making modalities and
complexity theory and the
systems theory informed sense that many
of us are familiar with
but she also adds um an element
of what i would call a contemplative
or non-dual embodied
participatory knowing so
um when i when i got to know her work i
was just so impressed
um epistemologically it it's
incredible compared to some of the
more um conceptual framework since
making frameworks that are out there so
i'm so excited to be here and
i will let bonita talk about what the
holo
is and um introduce the session
um i assume we will be having a q a
portion
and for that portion just put your
questions in the chat
um prefix them with cue or question
um so that i can see them plus one if
you think a question is good
and i will field those questions
all right over to you benita
wow this is really exciting okay so
the holo is um a neat
metaphor and image where you think of
like the pre-revolutionary
uh soldier people going into the hollow
to discuss the revolution
and here in connecticut we have what's
called the charter oak
where our original charter uh for
uh connecticut um was was
hidden inside the hollow of a tree um
hollows are these ravines where you go
at night or
pre-dawn uh so to be to be secret group
of revolutionaries um and
um it's great to have this run into
halloween uh so um
i want to frame this a couple of
different ways uh this
this uh series is an experiment
because one of the things we're trying
to or i'm trying to do
or we're all trying to do is talk less
about something
and immerse into it so i could blah blah
blah
on the difference between cross
paradigmatic multi-paradigmatic and
trans-paradigmatic i teach primarily
for all my workshops are designed for
postal formal learners
and post-formal learners are somewhere
in this
this arena so cross-paradigmatic means
i can sit inside of science
and look at philosophy or i could sit
inside of structuralism
and look at science right so i i'm
crossing from the i have one paradigm
where i'm looking at the other
and you see this happening primarily
this is what's happening
in the sense making space this level of
conversation
and then you'll have multi-paradigmatic
often called trans
paradigmatic but it's not and
multi-paradigmatic means
yeah i could enter in quantum mechanics
this framework with you
let's enter into complexity theory let's
enter into metapsychology
so i have the ability to occupy
many different paradigms and live there
and you see
also see this as part of the skill you
all have
in taking and taking these video you
know these videos here you need to be
multi-paradigmatic or else you'd just be
complaining you know that you don't get
it
what we're going to try to do here is uh
trans-paradigmatic
that means you're not
actually entering into these paradigms
as if they were separate worlds
but you're actually kind of having some
kind of
experience of them melting into each
other
and part of this experience in
post-formal learning
is very synesthetic visual
if you can use a lot of multimedia to to
encourage and invite the mind not to
clamp down and jump
into a paradigm but experience as
if you're the sun and there's those
constellations of worlds
um that's what we're going to try to do
and that's the last definition of the
hollow you have to kind of keep your
mind hollow so the
interplay of paradigms you know so then
you say well where are you coming from
and what we're hoping is that where
you're coming from
is emerges through takes on a new shape
so this is uh the conceptual framing
of what we're going to do to to do
together
um and obviously it's very experimental
but i think you all are up for it so let
me share my screen
oh let me say this so the way we're
going to do this is i'm going to
present in this kind of trans
paradigmatic way
uh the the first screen is not like that
it's another frame but then we're going
to get into this transparent
presentation um and then for the q a
we can come back down to conceptual
rationality for questions so that we can
kind of
mentalize or or get our get our uh
really be able to chew into some of the
concepts so it's not like the idea is
just to
to not hone in on some uh
uh teaching points so the question in a
can be
could be more rigorous in a conventional
way all right
so um
so what we are going to enter into
is this slide is to remind us
of what's in the sense making series
this is kind of an interesting slide
of a civilization that's come and gone
let's say
here's a remnant of a civilization and
there is this sense
that we are working in the sense making
se
seen with uh being on the verge of
bifurcation events catastrophic collapse
time in between worlds so we want to
enter into
this mean space that is
holding a lot of what we do here at the
store
right so this is a slide of of
some kind of remembrance
of that
what we're going to talk about today is
ta or over this series are the way we
have our metaphysics how modern minds
construe time change and causality
and that in my opinion these have to
actually
change to different types
of mental models in order for us
to move beyond modernity and
post-modernity
so a lot of the conversation
about civilization collapse
metapsychology etc is very interesting
but for me as long as it's inside the
same paradigm
that depends upon modernity's
notion of time modernity's motion of
change
and modernity's notion of causality i
don't think it's radical enough
i just this is gonna the hypothesis in
the whole
slideshow in the whole series so
we'll look at these specifically and see
see if these are actually changing in
our consciousness
um how does this fit into the some of
the other sense making series
um some of the sense making series uh
have a geohistorical frame
so we talk about globalism and the rise
of neoliberalism
uh media the internet exponential tech
and climate i would call that a
geo-historical frame
they're looking at time change and
causality
inside this geo-historical frame others
have a developmental frame the
development of the human
so we have cultural complexity cognitive
complexity
and psychologically complexity and they
also have
a a modern notion of time
change and causality we're going to look
at
um change we're going to look at sense
making from an evolutionary frame
and with evolution it's a directionless
change
right so in the geohistorical frame in
the developmental frame
you're always kind of your your notion
of causality is always from here
to better development better progress
you know
there's a there's kind of a linear
trajectory or direction
you're aiming for but an evolution
doesn't have a direction
so we're gonna try to think of sense
making
as a directionless change that happens
to us
that something we can't know beforehand
or explain afterwards
but something we can learn how to do so
the great apocalypse changes in history
like people learning how
having language symbolic language nobody
knew how to do that
you couldn't sense make your way into
learning language
it's evolutionary change that happens to
us
so this is kind of a different way to
hold um
the framing that we're using now the
interesting thing
is um with an evolutionary frame
your by you have bifurcation events
that change the nature of
thought beforehand and the nature of
thought
afterwards so it's very hard to use
the exis the the
sense that we make in modernity
to predict the sense we will make
after modernity because sense making
itself
evolves so for example
in the magical mind in the epic that
geps are called magical
they didn't like make sense of things
they didn't like try to go out
have common shared explanatory systems
the magical structure of consciousness
the the way we would call sense making
is just what works
what works is ritualized in collective
mimetic behavior
because what doesn't work dies out
people don't survive
and that's their sense making frame
they never said why does it work with
the mythical
structure of consciousness you start to
have this question why does it work
and you get a narrative story or a myth
about why it works
but there's no empirical correspondence
it's like
why does the sun shine because zeus gets
in his chariot you know this does not
a really a one-to-one correspondence but
you see the
question of why comes up in the mythical
mind
in the mental structure of consciousness
is the modern
way we think of sense making so i'm
asking to step back and think even
sense making even asking like why can we
make sense of the world or we should be
making
sense of the world if there's a war on
sense making
has a specific evolutionary apocalyp
time frame of modernity so this is a
really big
you really have to step back and
understand this
you want this very very
metacognitive perspective on this or a
transparent dramatic
so in mental structure of consciousness
and modernity
sense making for us is shared
explanations of how
how it works in order to predict aside
and control outcomes
right so the question i just want you to
maybe
feel into in in just for a short moment
is when did the world stop making sense
for you
and when you feel in that you'll
understand what making sense to you
means
that you lost something or something
the loss of shared shared explanations
or the loss
of predictability and control
or the loss of something right so when
did the world stop making sense for you
and what does making sense to you mean
you still have the bible story
right that would be a mythic explanation
what was removed from that
now another thing i want to talk about
modernity is modernity has not made
sense
for a lot of people ever
okay it doesn't didn't make sense
doesn't make sense for the orangutan and
the palm forest of course that's not a
person it doesn't make sense for the
camera
people that sort you know live through
world war one in world war
ii doesn't make sense for the people in
the holocaust it doesn't make sense for
homeless people it doesn't make sense
for a lot of people
for a lot of people modernity has never
made sense
this is just true this is just true
and for some people like a 14 year old
girl in africa who just graduated from
school and started
an ngo it's just now beginning to make
sense
in this notion of sense-making and
modernity
so we have to get a really very clear
on what we're talking about we're
talking about the war on sense making
for many people modernity has never made
sense
so this too is an evolving
metamorphing kind of game
so this is the framework in which this
series
operates in it's much different
than my work is really much different
than a lot of other people in this space
but i want to really
enable you to enter into this
transparent
view of what we're going to deal with
here
so i don't i'm not able to read the chat
uh and do this at the same time so if
you see something come up that
needs clarification in the chat just uh
shout it out
okay so let's um that's all framing
let's
enter this uh oh i think there's one
more thing
so in the end so where are we going
i want to give you the goal when we
start because
the in-between is kind of confusing
i'm going to predict that sense making
in the
modern sense is shifting from sense
making
to sense fullness
i could ramble on for hours about why i
think that's the case but i don't want
to do a conceptual
kind of evidential
thing here but that's where i think
we're going
and that we are moving from an
information commons and shared
explanation
which is how we try to make sense of
things now
and that's in the past that's that's
like
trying to make sense in a magical sense
that that i think
is not recoverable and that's okay
because i think we're moving to an
understanding and relational
intimacy what i call senseful
co-presence this is why yankaporta
is is interesting again and all these
you see all these
moves toward what looks like
pre-modernity
but it's a it's a hybridization to get
out of
modernity
so i just give you the end at the
beginning so you can see that there's
there's some kind of uh narrative arc
in this presentation so we don't have to
uh we can talk about this in the q a
that's what the q a
is for but we don't have to
um unpack that right now i think you can
get kind of get a hit of what that is
and i think if you think about it you'll
see this is leaking in
already you can see these moves
happening
and me frankly i don't want
to spend my time in the information
commons and shared explanation space i'm
a i'm a future junkie
all my energy is in like okay that's
irrevocably past
can we can we support can we birth
what wants to emerge
okay
so for me
the meta in meta modern this is part of
the our sense making space
must point to the ability to take a
perspective
on both modernity and post-modernity
now i leap i lump those two together
because they both come from the same
metaphysics of time change and causality
one's a critique on the other
but they assume the same modern
categories of time change and causality
so to me they're the same
and to go meta on that in the sense of
this trans-paradigmatic
is to be able to examine it as if from
without
and there's a really interesting
question is like
where is the without how can we get
out of modernity and post modernity
able to examine it and talk about it and
this is just
a little slide that kind of illustrates
for me that modernity and post-modernity
are in a metaphysical loop
because they rely on the same
primary categories metaphysical primes
of time
change and causality and if you change
them you've changed everything
we can we can look in the past and see
in
our evolutionary anthropology that
these conceptions have changed
and they're changing again
so for me to be sufficiently meta and
metamodern
is not just to be a next move on this
modernity post-modernity line
it's to categorically change
these metaphysical primes and to
let them go
so we can look back in time
and see that cultural artifacts art oral
history philosophy religion and science
can be read as dispatches from the times
so instead of looking at them and seeing
them as
past over
done with that would be
a modern way of looking at time it's
passed it's over it's done
we can look at them as that they've been
written in stone
to speak to us as modern people
you see the difference so instead of
looking at them as
another time they're dead they're over
with
now we're here we can say no they've
been
written in stone to speak to
us as modern people there
the text is only relevant now
and this is what gemster saw this is how
the buddhists think of
you know um maybe the way
they thought of the torah and the
buddhists think of these secret texts
that
they are dispatches from their times
we see there were times of deep
apocalypse change when one form of human
consciousness was replaced by another so
what they're telling
us is look you were different before
we were different before
we see periods of in betweenness when
the old structure no longer work
but the new structure is not yet to come
and i would argue this
is we're in a period of in between now
so what we could do is dispatch what it
feels like to be here
to our future selves
that what we write and what we say and
what we do at the stoa
is a record dispatch to our future
selves and
only they will be able to make sense of
it but not in the way we make sense of
things but in the way
they are making sense of things so this
is a way to really get into like
post-formal learning like
these creative imaginaries you get out
of the time frame
a past present and future and you start
to
create imaginary worlds that could be
so just like we look in the past and we
don't instead of saying
that's done and over with let's be
archaeologists about it
we can look into the past as if
it's speaking to us this is who you were
this is what we wanted you to know
and then we can imagine ourselves in a
time in between where we're not making
sense of things
and what we write and what we think and
all the confusion we are in
are actually dispatches to our future
selves
so they can figure out where we've been
maybe it's not ours to do
and this shows the continuity of mind
and life
in time it's very transpersonal
trans-sequential
move on
okay so here we are
we are in a time zone that has the
characteristic
of both being a frontier in a war zone
and this is where the
word dispatch and you want to dispatch
things from the war zone
back home you want to dispatch from the
frontier back home
and we are in this time zone we are the
explorers and survivors
and we are writing to you the people of
the future
this is what we're doing here in the
hollow we're dispatching what it's like
to be in this time between
worlds that feels a little bit like a
frontier and a little bit
like a war zone and we are writing to
you the future
people of the future
perhaps you will be able to make sense
of the things that elude us here
see this is something we can do here in
this time in between worlds
perhaps these dispatches will help you
make sense of where you are
knowing how perilous and wayward a
journey we have
undertaking to get there this is the
sense fullness of this time in between
worlds
these writings this slide show we'll
look at
are dispatches from the time between
worlds
to a time when a new world takes its
place
that's what we do here in the hollow
we're gonna hide this these dispatches
in the hollow of the tree
people discover them when the new world
takes its place
the sensefulness of this activity
now you're going to see we'll get we
each slide switches worlds so we're
playing in this like
we're okay we really inhabit this world
now we're gonna
boop we're gonna we're gonna work with
saying this in a different world they
they don't follow sequentially
this is trans deregmatic thinking
okay so this is an art installation that
was
um inspired by timothy morton's notion
of hyper objects
and one of the things okay this is a
dispatch
i'm going to dispatch this into the
future
this dispatch is that the metaphysics
that underlie both modernity and
post-modernity
have not only primed the current meta
crisis so i would
i would argue someone said the other day
on cap that capitalism you know
underlies just about everything and i
agree with that but underneath
capitalism
is the metaphysics of modernity
time change and causality how we
construe them
made the design of capitalism
possible this is why indigenous people
didn't
create capitalism because they don't
understand time change and causality
different
so i'm saying that not only have they
primed the current medical crisis
but they create this reaction in us
that in which we continue to exert
upward pressure
towards civilization collapse so as long
as we
address the metacrisis from within
the metaphysics of modernity and
post-modernity we will continue
to exert upward pressure towards
civilization collapse
now the the good news is that the
pressure towards civilization
collapse is making our heads wobble like
mine
these half-born ideas that we have
because our minds
can't make sense of things that upward
pressure is also exerting an
evolutionary pressure
to think outside these categories
so this happened for example in the
axial age
and plato was very cognizant that he was
using his mind in a different way
he had a word for it called diuresis
which is the word we get dialectical out
of this is how
has happened before these transmutations
these
metamorphic changes in
the architecture of mind
so for me this upward pressure is also a
sign
that we're using the uh metaphysics of
modernity and and as i keep saying it
modernity means both modernity in its
critique which we call post-modernity
so here's something that i would say is
not
looks like not upward pressure and this
is
a quote from david chandler
an era of conceptual closure the
metaphysics of modernity and
post-modernity
one is modernity one it's the critic and
the metaphysics are the same so they
close each other
this participation would include
and would of necessity include acting
our way
into new ways of thinking right not
trying to make sense in order to choose
what to do
but just acting and the
acting itself
will catalyze and support new ways of
thinking this is how we learn when we're
children
we just act we act we act out we push
boundaries
this creates a generative learning loop
and then he writes to become
experimenting compositional and playful
persons
fully aware of our lack of causal
knowledge
and confident and at home with
contingency in the unexpected
sense fullness play fullness
not sense making
to creatively engage with emergence
itself
thus turning problems or threats into
new opportunities
and to see that the problems themselves
point to
openings where new opportunities
lay
and i really like to slide i should
remember
who the artist is but um
yeah and i think a lot of the stoic
sessions are
are coming into this right i mean
the fact that there's so much conceptual
stuff in the con story sessions and then
there's all this playful
uh irreverence that is held sacred
and to really understand that this is
probably the bigger piece of the pod
like what would it be to does this slide
make sense
no but it's sense full and can we do
senseful acts
in a playful and compositional way i
think this is
this is what is being called forth
now to people who want to make sense of
the world it'll seem deviant or
silly or stupid or pre-rational
or crazy
that's the way they can interpret it
um so we're going to talk about
metamorphosis
this metamorphosis of mind is driven by
pressures that run counter this is
another david chandler
quote or excerpt adaptation
what we need to know is that that is
driven by pressure so what i call these
evolutionary pressures that run counter
to the modern mind's
upward path it operates through
counter-systemic approaches okay so
not complexities theory and more systems
thinking and more
cybernetics and more um
and more you know all this analysis it
runs
counter to that and they destabilize the
modern imaginaries of progress
civilization and development so what
he's saying
is that these this metamorphosis he's a
post-anthropic
writer which means uh he decenters from
the uh the the idea that the humans
are at the center of the universe and
the human thinking
um so what he's saying is that we need
to challenge these systemic
what it's like an arms race of
complexification around
progress civilization and development
and challenge
our fixed and empty framework of time in
space with ourselves at the center
this is part of this metamorphosis
and so when you're doing sense making at
this scale
this is what you're trying to this is
like part of your detector
like is that there's always progress
in development and civilization must go
on and get better
and then there's a techno fix and this
and that this is all
part of modernity's impulse in
compulsion
as we face environmental destruction at
a planetary scale an
existential risk at a global scale
we must examine our stories that stick
firmly to the modern imaginaries
since they emphasize our separation of
nature and destroy our shared
genealogy with the life force of the
earth
so a lot of people talk about in these
in some of these conversations about
having
a new shared imaginary but
when they say that they're still inside
notions of progress civilization
developmental bias and the notion that
the
people at the center of the universe
it's not radical enough
it's not a new imaginary it's still
stuck in the old story as charles
eisenstein would say
and i would say that the news story as
chandler says
has to be based on a different
metaphysics of time change and causality
and we're going to look at those three
in the next sessions
very very closely so they're coming the
the details coming
so for me i do not intend to drive
thinking
up toward increasing complexification
i intend to drive thinking down to its
metaphysical roots
it doesn't make it easy to do it's less
complex but it requires a metacognitive
insight down to the fundamental
formative metaphysics that constrain our
thought
now there is this concept
of theory constitutive
metaphor which means all our theories
are based upon a kind of
mental model or a metaphor of how it
works
so for example we our conception of time
is
always spatial like a timeline
and everything that happens in the
in the going forward
is progress and everything that's in the
past is primitive
this is a fundamental metaphor that we
use
when we talk about civilization
and then we equate progress with
complexification so if it doesn't get
more complex
we don't think it's progressive and we
don't aim that for that in the future so
these these metaphors get us all tangled
up into
trivial tautologies really
right so the same way that we think
modernity you hear this over and over
again and
i say too and i'm not going to say it
anymore we say
modernity has benefited
many people and then here are the
problems yeah but
that's because we equate modernity with
more complex with it must be better
despite a lot of evidence that modernity
has
not really been very good for a lot of
people
and a lot of living creatures we have no
evidence
to say that because all our evidence is
based upon the assumption that more
complex and a certain type of progress
is better we're in this closed
metaphysical loop
and this is what we have to get out of
this is what
we need to come to terms with
that maybe modernity is not better
than pre-modernity or maybe there's no
way to judge
all you can do is live in the time that
you live in
for many people modernity has not
been better and maybe for the majority
of people
it's not better
it's more complex more technologically
sophisticated
but you but you you can't equate that
with better
and then say well then i just prove
maternity is better and that's what we
do
we live longer but we have mental health
issues
oh but that's better because we can
quantify that we live longer
you can't hold core on what better means
and doesn't mean and then prove with
that definition that things have gotten
better
but you're stuck in a metaphysical loop
because modernity
only counts some things as better and
those things are modern
can you see what i'm saying here this is
really important for us to understand
the limitations of a closed metaphysical
system
loop in our minds
yes changes has happened it is what it
is
there's no way to prove it's better
after a bifurcation event
when we're no longer modern what
is better will be redefined
in its own terms and then you could
argue it's better
so we really have to be careful we
really have to have a lot of epistemic
humility
when we're taking on these projects of
speaking
from modernity for modernity
we have to look at modernity from
another place
and that's a hard move it doesn't mean
that theory gets more complicated but
the
metacognitive move is not simple
there's a level of clarity and awareness
that is required
and i think this yeah so these stories
this is the last slide for today
these stories of separation and
alienation
are consequences of reasoning from a
particular set of metaphysical primes
associated with the mental structure of
consciousness
from which the modern world in its
sequel the postmodern
are scripted perhaps the term
modern in metamodern reflects the
continuance of the same old metaphysical
architecture
in new conceptual bottles but for me it
signals a response
that we must look at modernity from
somewhere else
and this somewhere else is our period of
latency
of a time between worlds
so that's the framing uh when we come
back
we're going to look at time in the next
session we'll look at change
and then we look at causality in
particular
as they live in the modern
mind and we'll look at alternatives
that are in the contemporary imagination
thank you bonita
are you interested in opening up for
questions at this point
or yeah let's see if there's some
questions
and i think we have um
an hour and 15 minutes
so if we spend 15 minutes on questions
we can preview time because i think i am
going to run
out of time in four sessions so we can
maybe have 15 minutes of questions and
then we'll run the
series on the slides on time and then
that can stew
in between the sessions if we don't have
enough questions and answers
sounds good so
peter sforza has a question would you
like to unmute and ask your question
peter
yeah thanks benita that was great thanks
rayne i had two questions one was
thinking about the anthropocene but i
think the more relevant one is coming up
now about
uh the anecdote or stories of the tower
of babel
and this sort of uh how
how presumptuous of us to continue this
upward
um idea that we can create this
um unification how do how do you have
you thought about the tower of apple
anecdotes
with regards to complexity and some of
this framing that you're
giving yeah you're right you're right in
my heart space here
um from a very early age i never
understood
that that story like
like why do you want everyone talking
the same
thing and i don't know if it's before or
after i understood evolution
but i remember very early on
i shuddered um and we know from
evolution you want
lots of different ways of making a
living well look at this when we
we get to one of the slides on donna
haraway and how
what we want is more ways of making a
living more languages
more small commons more hybridization
when we look at um civilization collapse
if we have ecological collapse the
reindeer people will probably live
so then we have to rethink what
resilience is and resilience
is um not to have one language and one
economy
and one hyper system um so
um but of course the um
yeah so so that's a that's i call it
also symbolic magnification
we used to every little clan used to
have all their
their totems and all their kings and
queens
mythology now we have like you know
uh symbolic magnification there's only
so many archetypes they apply to
everything
this is a reduction of the human
potential
this is a reduction of psychic
imaginary it's a all these things are
highly reductive and therefore
because they've capitalized under a few
winners
you know there's a three or four big
archetypes uh they're very fragile
it's not resilient and so
you can see in a lot of the conversation
in civilization collapse
even if they're talking about resilience
they're still looking for
like we need a shared common imaginary
we need a cl
you know it's it's still in the wrong
direction
and that's the developmental bias of
progress is an accumulation
of a unification kind of thing so
um for me you can't
you can't it's like you can't have your
cake and eat it too
and um yeah
that that i get that hit right there
with the tower of babel story
um yeah thanks that was great
i like the resilience comment too it's
my saying for the summer has been that
consilience ate resilience for breakfast
and meaning that we still need to be
resilient but there's
there's more to it than that yeah and
and when we look at um
uh change we're gonna look closely at
the panarchy cycle and how people have
co-opted the notion of resilience
and turned it into the same logics that
has
brought us to fragility like we just
can't get
out of that mindset
okay a question from kim
go ahead yeah
hi bonnie thanks for this
this is just um you know
it feels like you're really pulling
together a lot of
felt senses that um and tangiblizing the
beautiful pictures by the way um and
uh the the question i mean this is just
you you answered a little bit of it just
now with
multiple languages but my question is
okay we are in this
you know in between worlds things and
the ability for us to go forward as i'm
uh as i get
and with what you're saying is for us to
use completely different ways of being
together
and how do we know i hate how questions
but what is the language that we
use as we uh interplay with others and
particularly
perhaps those who are really based in
the modern post-modern world
to engage at this
or begin to engage at this level i mean
this is the always the question well how
do we do this how do we do this so i'm
gonna throw it back at you
but kind of with that idea of
languages um and being
senseful within this context that we're
in
this in this olympic space between
worlds if that makes sense
yeah so i don't know how we talk about
that
i don't know how we language that i
think we
experiment which we all are doing
um hopefully one of the skills this
session will build is try not to do that
and then if you try not to do that then
you have
nothing to put in its place and then you
just have to
be there like if i don't think of if
then how do i think of change
and then and then this is a great
meditation this is a
you know i shared this story in one of
my store sessions when i was
doing this dialogue this workshop in san
francisco
and then sorry for all said what if
there's no if and no then
ah now something cracks in my head that
whole way of trying to figure out
causality without if then
he made it me aware that the if then
itself
is a certain assumption can we examine
why the brain does that why does your
mind do that
what if i don't let my mind do that uh
well you know maybe then i go and drink
a beer or if i'm peter lindbergh i smoke
a cigar
i don't know but you start to
really understand the nature of that
mind
now i'm with them because
you guys can ask questions that that
are previewing what we're going to be
doing but then this will give us
capacity when it comes on
and so like like um
another another reason why i call this
the hollow
is because your mind is like
is like the hollow of a tree be careful
what you put in there
right and now i'm not going to
go to the buddhist thing and say
your mind should be empty
i think your mind should be creative and
you should be aware of the
constructs the fundamental
metaphors that you use to examine
something
and how do we change those how do we
change those now here's where your mind
goes okay here's with them
how do i change those so the world gets
better
you see that's what comes in it wants to
come in
how do i examine that so it gets better
and then you say
no i have to i have to let that
orientation go too
we know change happens uh
why am i preoccupied with this
qualitative measurement of better when i
just
said there's no way to know what better
is
because when catastrophic change happens
what we say is better also changes
because our mindset will change
so um um
if you're lucky these kinds of things
that you do when you're
meditating on these things uh create fun
enjoyment and you laugh because because
it's like like kids when they can't get
out of a maze and they laugh
but they're really trying and if you're
not lucky it drives you crazy
and you you commit suicide or something
but
that's something of the process that
goes
goes into here and you know i'm sharing
quotes from people who've written
cool books that i call them post
anthropic
and we like to get them on the store
we're talking about that but
these things are happening in people's
minds to be able to
you know to think in this way to
experiment in this way
uh and we'll meet some of them as we go
on
and so uh one of the reasons why i'm
doing all this framework framing is
because you can read them
and you can capitalize it with a modern
mindset and
if you read these people carefully
they're saying something else i think
they're saying something more like
we're saying here
one of the biggest breakthroughs that we
had when i was running a lot of
collective insight
processes here is there was a group that
was meeting quite often
and we were examining the contraction
you have
when you're not understood by other
people
but it got
it got foregrounded once we realized
that something
some of the tension that seemed to be
going on was really
that there was a fear someone said oh no
it's a fear and at first it was like i
don't i don't feel like i belong but
that was like stupid
and what we did was this thought of
experiment we said
how much of my experience like if two
people see
an accident and the cop
asks each one of them what happened
you'll get two different stories
sometimes very competing stories
even when we look at the freaking
cameras on the cops
it doesn't it doesn't adjudicate the
perspectival nature
of the experience so then we said
here sitting here in this collective
space
how much experience you think we're
actually sharing
like we realized that we had this
assumption that we were sharing the same
experience but that our language
was different right so we were trying to
semantically map
and make sure that we're all on the same
page and we got
so we realized that maybe we didn't we
weren't having the same experience
then we did this thought experiment what
if we actually share
no experience zero no meaning making
no sense making everything we say
has we live in our own little bubble
and we all got like you know when you're
in these sense-making spaces it's quite
psychoactive
and then we realized that the world
would still hang together
so then we realized that the whole
construction of that question
is just based upon some kind of faulty
metaphor
of do things connect or they don't
connect and stuff like that
like the whole the whole thing is
based upon assumptions that things
connect in a certain way
that things are shared in a certain way
that things make sense in a certain way
and we realize yeah actually they do
connect
they do make sense and there is meaning
but we have no freaking idea how
and there's no sense to try to make that
happen because it either doesn't happen
or doesn't happen
which case we it's not a question at all
because we've got something like that
and this is kind of a little bit of the
attitude
a little bit of the attitude about
evolutionary change it's not
something we can work on it works on
us so
you know it looks like i'm working on it
because i'm working
in it but there's
you have to you have to there's a sense
in which
you're not a naive realist but you're
naively take reality
to be real and that it works
and that you can trust it and it does
what it does and you can't do
any better there's a there's a certain
smell in these sense making spheres
i call it the god problem you probably
heard me talk about it before because
i this liberated me i worked so hard
to help people make humanity healthy
and then i realized that it's like you
have a god problem
that you think you could do better than
nature
or cosmogenesis or god like you really
think you can figure it out
right and this it's not possible it's
not
possible to operate on the world from
that
from that leverage point that vantage
point
so then the question is how can you
operate in the world
ah you have a vantage point to operate
in the world
so um
yeah but what you can do is operate on
your mind from that vantage point
it's just really really hard to do to
understand that these are the traps that
your
these loops that you're stuck in
thank you i i just want to also say
what i'm discovering is operating with
the world and that's that creativity
that what you're talking about
is you're watching your mind you're
growing you're playing
you're watching and it's just like
this fun but
kind of wild ride almost yeah
it's wow yeah thanks
so benito we're at the 15 minutes of q a
um so you said you wanted to move on to
some slides on time
i just want there's some great questions
in the chat and i just want to highlight
a couple
and let you decide benito whether you
want to answer them
now or later because they're
definitional questions and
as this is the first session that might
be valuable so
there were there was one question on the
definition of better
yeah and then there's another question
on your definition of metaphysics
okay yeah no i said if we didn't have
enough questions we could do that but
this is
this is i think we should spend time on
the questions
okay so the question of better
um a lot of these questions i have to
pivot to stories because it gets way too
complicated to
metatheorize around it but what one of
the things we'll
look at uh well we'll look at this
notion of better
progress um
later but i use the term
i borrowed it from yonkaporta and he
talked about he said my people we don't
have this notion of progress we have
this notion of increase
and i wrote that in a paper and the
editor said
i i can't see any difference like
so it's very tricky because we can't say
increase
eventually we see it as better
or progress right and
we can see increase it seems
quantitative
how can i understand that qualitative so
um
it's very hard it took me a while to
figure out
how to relate to this term increase
without subtly
having this notion of better or progress
so this this is very very hard to do the
fact that it's hard to do makes me very
stubborn because like i don't want my
brain to like
clamp down like that right um
so in the paper we're working on a
paper i wrote this part of this is this
research i did
i was trying to figure out how to
explain to this editor that
increase doesn't mean progress and so
the metaphor i used is
um
and let me see and tell me if this works
and trying to
decouple the notion of increase
with progress and so i wrote
the way increase the way
frost concentrates sugar in the fruit
or the way trouble
concentrates conversation so for me
increases this notion of concentration
not accumulation
so that's one way of relating
that i relate to this notion
of increase but i don't really know
how young caporto's native
or natural way of relating to that that
word
is so
that's not increasing complexification
the way trouble concentrates
conversation you wouldn't say that was
progress
wouldn't say it's necessarily complex
doesn't have to complexify you might
not be able to talk but it increases
it's like becomes more senseful
senseful and if you know about
wine and stuff and why birds eat the
berries off the trees after the winters
because the fruit gets concentrated
so that's the that's the metaphor that i
thought of
but it's not easy to
come into relationship with the term
increase
uh without conflating it with better or
progress is it better to have trouble
when you're
trying to talk to someone
no i wouldn't say it's better
was that helpful for that question i
mean there's a
it's like a handicap and working at this
level of
uh insight that's great
did you want to say anything about your
definition of metaphysics
oh yes so um i should have said that at
first so
i have um uh
i use charles hart shorn's definition of
metaphysics
and metaphysics is uh
like the deepest categories
or metaphors or mental models
that underline and construct make make
thought possible but also constrain
thought
to those metaphors that architecture
those movements those categories okay so
i call them metaphysical primes they're
very very very
deep in structuration of thought
um and not even conceptual thought um
even reaction like you see something and
you move this way
or that way or right
in left brain uh schemas is really a
very very deep metaphysics right because
we're constrained
to that bicamerality
uh yeah so are they accessible yeah
that's what we're doing here
and i suppose the ones that are not
accessible
we're not gonna be working with them
um um but a lot of um
you know that's what insight practice is
for me
i think collective insight practice the
way i teach is trying to get it
at these these really deep habits
of or architecture or schemas of thought
so we can disembed from the constraints
and when whitehead for example wrote
process in reality
he was doing speculative metaphysics he
knew he was he thought that there was
a usefulness for it to come up with
reasonable theories of the way
the world might work based on different
ways of looking at
for him change and relationship and
we'll
we'll look at some of whitehead's
metaphysics as alternatives
to the metaphysics of modernity
thank you are you good for more
questions
yeah yeah we'll just just uh they go
they're great questions and i think
uh you know the more understanding we
can get now once we get into
the conceptual territory the more um
the better it'll be great
better um lots of
it'll increase our experience very good
hugely bigly
concentrate that that wisdom um
peter lindbergh lots of plus ones
all right uh so there's a question here
bonita but if anything is salient for
you
feel free to respond to it so i'll read
it out
recently in stewarding the stoa others
have been encouraging me to scale this
place
have collective goals for it etc this is
somewhat scrambling the way i've been
operating here since the beginning
really
what i've referred to as listening to
the daemon
feeling into this pressure on a
sensefulness level i sense like urgency
and behind that i sense fear on a
propositional level i hear
see modernist frameworks goals scaling
truth etc
what is the interplay if any between
having a bad relationship with fear and
modernity's proclivity for control
yeah so um
i think what i'm just going to tell you
how i teach fear
in my my course because we just we do a
module on the affects
so fear is the contracted form of
seeking
their neuro anatomically neurochemically
and neurodynamically in the same path
so if you have fear you ask your ques
so you can feel the toggle right so when
you're in the woods and you're looking
for something then there's fear right
there they're
so fear is the energy of seeking
contracted
so what you want to do is use its energy
for free
and you want to try to orient it toward
to the seeking
what are you seeking well you don't
really know because the damon is seeking
so you can orient toward the seeking
itself
and you're going to toggle between high
times and fear
because it's the same neural anatomical
neurodynamical
path this is true for animals also
now the expanded form of fear and
seeking is awe
that's the highest expanded form and
that's also
in the same path so the vajrayana awe
is the baby sister of awe is fear
in the middle in the middle son is
seeking
and the grand old damn at the end is
just standing in awe
and this woman diane uh
eileen russell
she noticed she's the one that put this
together this framework together
and she called them the tremulous energy
because when you're fearful
you're trembling and when you're seeking
and you're really you're trembling and
when you're standing in awe
you're trembling and she started to see
these
uh vagal patterns and stuff like that
so when you're working with fear you
just know it's energy for free
it's seeking energy it still has energy
it's just a little contracted
because you can't like boom you can't
like
be in expanded form all the time there's
always breathing in and breathing out
so so uh that can be your friend
that can be your friend
is that helpful or do you want a
clarifying question
uh that's very helpful and something i'm
going to
noodle on i also wonder if you had
anything about the other part of the
question how it relates to modernity
is there something like inherently
pathologically embedded in modernity
they don't have a good relationship with
fear
i would say that the beginning of your
question was right you're detecting
some kind of pathology of modernity to
make more sense of what you're doing
to wrap it up to to
i mean i feel that too i mean okay i'm
not very proud of this
but like sometimes i want to be more
like them because i get bigger likes on
your store channel i
get more watching you know i mean this
happens in our mind it's like bonnie if
you just got like real
then maybe you know if you just
downloaded your conceptual territory
uh but that's not what we're seeking you
see that's not
that's not what's operating in us so i
get it
and um and there's no right or wrong in
this it's just
it's just where's the energy moving and
um
um when i you know there's lots and lots
of
good video channels and i think that
uh i don't think they have a very long
shelf life except maybe joe rogan
and you know um
i think what what what the trade-offs
are making i think they're really as
long as they keep
keep increasing like you know then uh
maybe it's a it's a good formula you
know um but yeah
they're they're it's it's not going to
you're not going to get like
the ratings or the spoils of modernity
if you're not playing that game
um yeah
thank you
so we're at the 75 minute mark i want to
ask you benita
yes if you have one or two more
questions that are standing out
sorry about the dogs
um question from andy i pasted it in the
chat andy feel free if you'd like to
ask your question so
bonita the whole process of doing the
hollow
if we look at it metacognitively how do
we incorporate play
rather than using a modernist framework
of a lecture based format
because what we're doing here is no
different than
you know a platonic uh
framework of
dialogue or talking at and
um i'm trying to cohere that with
uh the content of what you've been
talking about
yeah that's a good question um and it's
funny because i heard
you say play and then when you say play
playtonic i
heard p-l-a-y tonic
tonic um okay so
um
see there you go um
uh so i always i i quite often
seem illogical or have performed a
contradiction i happen to think
this is a form of high play like for me
it's
it it's quite playful um
i understand the cognitive load and the
conceptual burden
and for some people this is this is
doesn't seem playful i spent a lot of
time
um choosing the the music at the
beginning
um because i think it's it's in your
face and it's playful
um so so
um and then i think energetically i try
to
be have playful energy um
but is it as good as like rolling in the
hay
and then sitting back and talking about
uh
modernity no i mean um now
i'm gonna say this that um
yeah so i would say this is playtonic
hopefully um and
um maybe i'll i'll look over my slides
and see if i can't put in some that are
more play-like because of that comment
um i don't you know
um how would you make it more playful
i i think the technology itself is not
very fun
um
well you know it's something for all of
us always to think about
um but i'm i'm wondering if just
thinking about the um structure of the
hollow or the stoa
or peter's concerns in a
uh modernistic framework of fear and
control
um if we throw all those out and go back
uh to primitive how would that look how
would our
interactivity be though limited by zoom
um
be playful because we we uh
we're kind of operating on the
perception that
uh there's a a goal to be had by doing
the hollow
there's an end point of skill sets or
thought processes we want to
evolve to after four sessions
as i and i guess what i'm confused about
is
um do i or the stoa
and this is to peter's journal from two
or three nights ago
um should there be a goal orientation
which is very modern post-modernistic
to the stowe or not
okay that's a bit that's a a
great re reframe all right i think that
uh one of the goals of let's say the
holo
is to build a skill there are some skill
building things in here
that i'm trying to sneak in but one is
to be able to be aware of your
architecture of your mind
now though just the way i i
talked to peter about fear in seeking
play is in the mastery stream so we
think of play
uh a play is not just light you know
sports and training and martial arts all
that is play
and play build skills and so one of the
sk
we could build skills here um
and um and primarily the one we're
building
is metacognitive capacity and that's a
kind of play
in the mastery sense um so
peter and i have talked a lot about what
if every conversation could build a
skill
that doesn't mean it has a goal right i
can teach you how to
shoot a gun and your goals could be
whatever
and so we actually talked about that
like that could be
a guiding principle where every
conversation builds a skill
doesn't download content doesn't aim for
a goal
and so that's i think very close to what
you're
asking and i would say that the skill
here
is um in the sense of mastery
is um an uh metacognitive awareness
being able to really get out and see
modernity from a place
outside of the categories of modernity
um
just a little bit um so that's
that's one thing it's not as
goal-oriented as some of these
these other things the second thing that
i'm
interested in and i had this
conversation before
with people that are also sense making
um some of my friends and colleagues
because i was wondering like like
that like what is the difference in my
approach than other
people's approaches and we i came in
dialogue with someone i came to the
conclusion that
in many respects other people
have an implicit goal they kind of know
what better is they kind of know that
they want to tweak the system
in this way and not others and what i'm
all about is injecting novelty into the
system
i don't know what way it wants to go but
we're so
habituated that i just want to inject
novelty into the system
and then i trust that as it gets shaken
up
it's going to go where it wants to go
because that's the inevitable anyways
it's going to be what it is so
my orientation to my work is to inject
novelty in the system
and i and in many other cases and this
might be the pressure that peter is well
where
where are you going with this and
um so that's another distinction that
that i
that i would make
um yeah
was that helpful close to the best i can
do
okay question from
tanya hewitt if you're here you can ask
your question
so benita i just wanted to thank you so
much for this
this is you know um when i was uh
doing my uh doctorate that i had one
single lecture on
um indigenous understanding of reality
and just as you were talking i was just
wondering if you uh have
if you believe that in dead indigenous
peoples
the ones who are kind of faithful to the
way that they have traditionally lived
are senseful in the way that they live
um okay so um this is an opinion
and there's always like a certain kind
of territory i enter in when it's just
an opinion
like i relate to it as an opinion um
i think there's very very few indigenous
people left in the planet
most of them are modern people
from a certain culture okay
so um
you see it's hard right were they more
senseful
in the past um yeah
um i would say in my definition of
senseful
it's comes after going through modern
modernity um
so i would say indigenous people are
more like sensing
their their perceptual organs are in
many cases
if they're truly indigenous as that word
means
are usually more alive you know they can
smell things they can see
things
they have more what we would call direct
perception sensory awareness
but i think since fullness for me uh
i would you i'm using the term as if you
have
you have to have gone through not
individually but humans have to go
through
uh modernity
even as an indigenous person you go
through modernity suffering it let's say
you didn't you didn't capitulate to it
but
you've gone through it suffering it does
that help
so the way i'm using that word that's
where i want it to
function
indigenous people never suffered
modernity are not the same as indigenous
people who suffer
modernity it's a it's a different
different thing and i'm not sure there
are any
of the other yet anymore
okay that was a great uh question one
more
if it's highlighted uh but i don't want
to
brain drain us um on this and then
destroy the fun yeah i i think
um i'm gonna call it now bonita we just
have a couple minutes left
um seems like a good stopping point and
i want to give you a chance to
share any closing remarks or foreshadow
our next session before i hand it over
to peter
yeah these are all great questions and
the ones that you
probably are going to be asking i think
they'll unfold
uh as we look at the detail and we get
the hang of it
uh um i'm so happy it seems like there's
there's a certain amount of tangibleness
that has landed
with you and this is a very very high
skill
that you are uh showing up with
and hopefully they all come back uh next
week because
um yeah we can build on what we're doing
today
awesome thank you benita um
peter awesome uh
thank you rayne and thank you so much uh
bonita uh this is uh awesome the series
is congealing a bunch of kind of threads
for me and i imagine a lot of people
here at the stoa um
yeah so i'm going to plug a bunch of
events uh just on the indigenous thread
we have kim talbear coming in to talk
about settler sexualities
uh on november 6th maybe gray's going to
host that one that's kind of related to
the pressures of modernity that we're
speaking on
um and next week we're going to launch a
really really cool
series which i'm excited about uh and i
might you know with my junk researcher
status at john vicki's lab we might have
some kind of interplay with it
um it's communitas club this is with
margaret who's also in the room
uh we're going to explore all these sort
of wee space intersubjective and
conversational modalities
uh we have a forced landry's ephemeral
process
we have uh kind of like reflective
structure dialogues have circling uh
entangled bodies so that series is going
to launch uh
i think on that's a tuesday october 13th
at 5 30 pm eastern time
and so you can help design it with us
too because that's what the launch is
about to kind of design this
maybe we can import these practices in
like we have with collective presencing
or empathy circles
and then maybe just mix them together uh
have bespoke
psychotechnology which brings me to the
next event i'll plug christian could you
um
mute yourself and plug your session
called bespoke psychotechnology that's
coming up
if you're still in the room christian oh
did christian leave
oh there we are well we can't hear you
um maybe i'll just melt maybe just speak
it and i'll just melt that
so anyways christian he's on mute uh
he's doing a session that's coming at
the stoa
let me find a date uh
october 24 a fourth it's bespoke
psychotechnology so the idea is taking
all these different psycho technologies
like practices
how can we stack them together mix them
up to create our own to kind of respond
to
the moment so like d dyi um diy
uh psycho technology and then uh we have
another event coming up uh
kim can you plug the event coming up in
about
30 minutes sure um
yeah ria bach who has worked with um
bonnie and uh it's called collective
presence thing and maybe some of you
have heard about it
i would just say it's part of what this
practice is that we've been talking
about today in the skills building
about listening collectively to
emergence
um and uh yeah
sort of speaking to and from the middle
and
that's happening yeah in 30 minutes for
an hour and a half but there's also
going to be another one for central
european timers
that we think is going to be um on
fridays
at 1 30 central european time so that
could be helpful
uh because we're getting a lot of people
very cool thank you kim yeah
that's growing the collective
presentation was quite exciting uh
lastly
our boy tyson um wagner uh you got two
events to cut
the plug and it's very playful uh so
you're gonna meet yourself and uh
talk about those sure thanks peter
thank you rayne and bonnie this i really
look forward to the rest of the series
um yeah the session on sundays is
flowing with unknowingness at 8
30 pm eastern and it's a very playful
space and so i encourage you to
come and see it as an opportunity to
take some risks
be fearless and play and experiment
as radically and wildly as as you like
with the way that you communicate and
express yourself
with words or sounds or otherwise and
then
that's sort of the place where we can
build a skillfulness
and a confidence with the modality and
then on mondays following daniel
schmuckenberger's digital porch
we will engage in a dialectic
through freestyle rap and spoken word
and practice rap unbattles
so if rap battles typically tear each
other down let's see how we can
use this modality together to
sharpen our thinking and to
have a lot of fun together and build
each other up and no experience wrapping
required
if you can speak and use your words or
even just make sounds
then i invite you to come participate
all right thank you
awesome yeah and i'll echo upon you
saying i have no idea what this space
called the still is all about but i know
we're here to play
uh so that being said you can check out
the website for more events uh the
patreon and the substance mailing list
again bonnie rain thank you and everyone
for coming today to play with us